Hey Fox, it is very important for you to have a health insurance policy of ₹15 to ₹1 lakh.  No matter which
insurance company it belongs to.
I heard this from
a personal finance educator who is
also a big Uber.  But is his
statement correct?  According to me, this
is absolutely wrong because having a
health insurance policy from any insurance company is
more useless than not having a health insurance policy at all because at the
time of hospitalization, you will be lying on the bed in the
hospital, there is no guarantee that any
health insurance
policy will give you the claim at that time
and those situations will be very bad situations.
You have to
purchase a health insurance policy from such a health insurance company
which gives you the claim when the time comes
and more importantly, gives you a hassle-free
claim.  So [ __ ], in today's video
I have brought to you a comparison of the
top three health insurance plans of our country.
Earlier you have seen in my videos the
comparison of top 10 health insurance plans and after that you saw the
comparison of top five health insurance plans.  I received calls from many viewers
and there was a demand to filter it further
and I have brought to you a comparison of the top three health insurance plans.
Watch this video till the end.  You
can share it with your friends and relatives
because someone else might be
planning to purchase a health insurance policy.
Also, if you have come to
Insurance Seva for the first time, then subscribe to Insurance Seva
and also press the bell icon.
[Music]
So let's start today's
video because it's very long, so let's get
straight to the point.
I have brought plans from three insurance companies, HDFC
ARGO ICC LBRD and Bajaj General Insurance
Company.  Earlier its name was Bajaj Allianz
and now its name has become BAJ General.
You are seeing six points on my screen
and these are the six points, these six points
tell the status of the insurance company.
Explains the fundamentals of an insurance company.
This tells you
whether the insurance company will be able to give you a hassle-
free claim or not when you go to the hospital.  So first of all let
us look at the complaint ratio.
How many complaints have been received against the insurance company in the Insurance Ombudsman
?  So first of all, there
were 1216 complaints against HDFC Ergo in
2023 and 24, which gives a ratio of 8.64 complaints per 1 lakh customers.
ICICI LBRD is at second place, the total number of
complaints against them was 914, the ratio comes out to be 3.15
and the third place will be occupied by Bajaj General
Insurance Company, whose total complaints were
511 and their average per lakh customers comes out to be
only 1.61, so these three companies
are fundamentally very strong.  If I
analyse the complaints,
you will see a little more complaints from HDFC Ago.
But if you talk about the plan, then the
best selling plan among these three companies is
Optima Secure of HDFC Ago.
So when the ratio comes out, the ratio
of all three companies will be almost equal.
Now let us talk about the claim settlement ratio,
HDFC Ergo has a claim settlement ratio of 99%.  That means, against
100 claims,
he has settled 99.  97% IC
LBA and 96%
Bajaj General Insurance Company.  Incident
Claim Ratio 81% HDFC Ergo 79%
IC LBRD and 74% Bajaj General Insurance
Company Incident Claim Ratio means
how many claims were settled against the total premium
?  Now we will also talk about solvency ratio.
Solvency ratio
indicates the financial status of the insurance company.
So here if we talk about HDFC Ergo
then theirs is 1.68.  Regulatory says it
must be 1.5.  That means
you should have ₹150 against a liability of ₹100.
But HDFC Ago has ₹168.
ICC LBA has 2.68 i.e. ₹268.
Against a liability of ₹100 and that is where
Bajaj is very strong in this matter.
He has ₹349 against ₹100.  That
means they have a solvency
ratio of 3.49.  Network Hospitals: This is also a very
important point.  However,
network hospitals do not matter much
because network hospitals keep getting de-panelled
and their panel also keeps running.   That
means it can be more or less.  There are 15,000
ICC Lobard, 14,000 HDFC Ergo and 15,000
Bajaj General Insurance Company.   The
reimbursement claim process
is online for all three companies.  First of all, if we
talk about HDFC Ergo, then make a bunch of all the documents.
Send it to K@HDCO.  The claim will be settled.
ICC LBA has their app IL
Care.  Upload all the documents on IL Care.
Your claim will be settled.
Similarly, Bajaj General Insurance
also has an app called Caringly Years.
You have to submit all your documents there and
your claim will be settled.
Before looking at other features, I think
we should also look at some of its special features,
those special features which make these plans a
little unique and different.
So first of all let us come to the
Elevate plan of IC LBA.  So they have a
feature called jump start.  By the way, almost
all insurance companies have now introduced this feature.  They
provide cover for some diseases from day one or from day 31.  So here
in Jump Start you will get coverage for hypertension,
diabetes, obesity, asthma and
hyperlipidemia from 31 days.
If there is a pre-existing element,
after paying a little premium additionally.  HDFCO
also has this.  You will get cover for these diseases like asthma, BP, cholesterol,
diabetes
from 31 days.  See Additional Premium.
But this feature is not available in Bajaj Aay KM Health
Care Plan.
ICC has power booster life time till
your time will keep on getting short multiple.  If you
take a policy of ₹1 lakh with add-on cover, then it will continue to
run for ₹20 lakh, 30 lakh, 40 lakh next year.  The
policy can reach Rs 1 crore in 10 years, Rs 2 crore in 20 years, Rs 3 crore in 3 years and Rs 3 crore in 30 years.
He has added Infinite Care.  That means Infinite
Care is an add-on cover.  If you add this,
unlimited claims can be made once in your lifetime.
Rest, unlimited sum assured,
unlimited restoration, same person same
illness will remain in all three policies.
Unlimited sum assured
option is also available with ICC.  That means you can take
unlimited sum assured.
You pay its premium.  Then there
is no problem with the claim.  After going to the hospital,
whatever claim comes, whenever it comes, the insurance
company will pay it.  Let's take a look at
HDFCO's Optima Secure plan.  So
here they have given plus benefit
in which they increase your time by 50% every year
till it becomes 100%.  This is a plus benefit.  There
is no no claim bonus.  It will
accumulate whether there is a claim or not.
Secure Benefit is a bit unique to them.
It provides double coverage from day one.
In a policy of Rs 10 lakh, you will get a cover of Rs 20 lakh from day one and
in a policy of Rs 25 lakh, you will get a cover of Rs 50 lakh.  It
is an inbuilt feature.  No additional
premium is required to be paid for this.  That means,
whatever time you are opting for,
we can claim double of it from the very first day.
They have protect benefit.
They have cover for consumable items inbuilt in the product benefits.
You will get the consumable item
inbuilt.  Restoration
benefit is available here, unlimited same person
same illness,
pet hood cover is available here by taking 5% premium additional, which
means you will also get maternity cover
in this plan.  Similarly,
you can also get maternity cover from ICLA.
There is also an add on cover.
Bajaj Alanj My Health Care Plan has a very
good feature.  OPD cover is unique.
They have provided inbuilt OPD cover in it.
Whatever premium you pay, take 200% OPD.
If your premium is ₹00 then
you can claim OPD of ₹40.00.
But that OPD is with capping.
If you get it reimbursed, you will get 80%
claim and there is a capping of ₹10 in it.  That means
you can get a
maximum of Rs 1200 in OPD.  Baby cover can be
reduced with a waiting period of one year.
Maternity cover is up to ₹1 lakh. Maternity cover can be
reduced after 2 years and can be taken even after one year.
This has been customized.
Home Nursing: If your sum assured is Rs 50 lakh, then you can get
home nursing care at ₹000 per day
and if your sum assured is above Rs 1 lakh, then
you can get home nursing care at ₹100 per day. There
is a baby care facility in this plan.  You will also get international coverage
in emergency conditions.  This also comes
with an add on cover.  Now let us take a
look at the basic features of these plans.
Here we will talk about the basic features.
So first comes sum assured.
So let's talk about ICIC LBAD.  They have
unlimited sum assured
options starting from ₹5 lakh and
also have a maximum cover of ₹3 crore.  In HDFCO, you will get cover ranging from ₹5 lakh to
₹1 crore and
in Bajaj Allianz, you can
get sum assured cover starting from ₹5 lakh to ₹1 crore.  The
minimum entry age is 18 years and there is no maximum age
limit in all three plans.  The
policy tenure can be
taken for 5 years in ICC LBA and the other
two policies have a policy tenure of 3 years.  The
variants are HDFC Ergo
Life Global, Global Plus and the family size is
two adults, four kids and two adults, three kids.
Under ICCMARD, we will talk about room rent
which is an important aspect
for any health insurance policy
because almost all the hospital
expenses are
linked to the room rent.  So,
you will get a single private AC room in ICC LBA's Elevate
plan, which you can also upgrade and downgrade.
HDFC Ergo
is inbuilt in Optima Secure.  There
is no room capping.  It can neither be downgraded
nor upgraded.
You will get a single private AC room which you can upgrade from
My Health Care of Bajaj Aya Bajaj General Insurance Company.   Let's
see more features.  ICU ICCU Up
to Sum Assured Copayment None.
Pre Hospitalization Post Hospitalization
90 & 180 Elevate 60 & 180 Optional in Optima
Secure and
My Health Care Plan of Bajaj General Insurance Company 30 60
90 180 You have to choose.
You will be charged premium accordingly.
You can also avail post hospitalization for 306, 90, 180 and 240 days.
Day care modern treatment is covered.  There
is no capping limit.  E-consultation for
critical illness is available in Optima Secure
and unlimited is available in Bajaj Alanj's
My Health Care plan.  ICC is
inside the LBD with add ons there.   If you
pay the premium you will get
teleconsultation, otherwise you will not get it.
Restoration Unlimited
Ambulance up to sum assured for same person same illness will
not be capped.  Air ambulance is also covered
in your ICC LB and HDFC Ergo but if we
talk about Bajaj Allianz, then air ambulance can be taken for Rs
10 lakh for Rs 5 lakh to Rs 1 crore and for Rs
20 lakh for more than Rs 1 crore.
No Claim Bonus
We talk about the inbuilt no claim bonus here.
So 20% yearly maximum will go up to 100.
Talking about the power booster in the ICC Labrador Elevate plan, it is
an add-on cover.  He will be completely separate from this.
Secure benefit is
50% yearly maximum 100% in your HDFCO Optima Secure,
this is plus benefit, no secure
benefit and if we talk about Bajaj General
Insurance Company's My Health Care Plan,
then there if your term sum assured is ₹
1 lakh, ₹3 lakh and ₹4 lakh then you will get
25% yearly and maximum up to 100% and
on term sum assured of ₹5 lakh or more you will get 50% yearly
and maximum up to 100% as no claim bonus.  The
waiting period for Home Care Domiciliary up to Sum Assured PED will be
36 months in all three policies.  Annual health
checkup is not inbuilt in ICC LB Elevate.   Comes
with add ons.  You will get it if you pay additional premium.
But in HDFC Ergo you will get it
inbuilt.  The maximum sum assured limit for ₹500 per lakh will be
₹1,000.
Bajaj Allianz has a list of these.   There
is a prescribing test.  You will get it on cashless basis.
Alternative treatment
which we call AYUSH.  All these treatments like Unani, Siddha and
Ayurvedic are
now covered in all three policies.  Maternity
is also included in all three policies.  If you
take add-ons in all three, maternity will be covered.
You will get up to sum assured inbuilt in Optima Secure in ICC LBA with consumable add on and also in Bajaj Aya My Health Care.
Wellness
programs up to 30% off can be availed
in ICC LB's Elevate plan.  Let's take a few
steps.  Some of you should keep yourself healthy.  If you go to the
gym, you will get their membership.
Along with this, whatever their app is,
your activity is tracked through the app.
Then you are given a discount on that.
You will get deductible options in HDFC Ago
's Optima Secure. Take deductible of ₹25, 50 and ₹1 lakh
and you can reduce the premium.
So Fox, these were
all the features of this plan and the fundamentals of the insurance company.
I have told you everything about all three plans.
Now finally comes the
matter of premiums because premiums
also decide which plan you will
purchase because you also have to look at your pocket.  The
budget also has to be looked at.
You should keep a budget of 3 to 4% for health insurance.  According to
me,
you should budget 3 to 4% of your annual income
for the premium.  Because only then
you can purchase a good health insurance policy.
For a sum of ₹25 lakh under the Elevate plan of ICIC LBA,
if you are 40 years old, live in Delhi NCR, have
two adults and two children, you will have to pay Rs
33,923.
In this I have taken no room capping.   That
means room rent capping has not been taken.
Power booster has been added.  And claim
protector i.e. consumable items
are also inbuilt in it.  So the premium I think is
economic.  Not very expensive.
Whereas HDFC Ago Optima
Secure will charge you ₹38,900 ₹59.   It will be a
little on the higher side.  But this 25
with 25 free day one will get a cover of 50 lakhs.
In this you will get consumable items
inbuilt.  Bajaj Ali will be a
little more costly than these two.
You will have to pay ₹40,290.  But you will
get OPD worth ₹80,000 every year,
which will be capped and if you
claim reimbursement, you will get 80% of it.
So these are their premiums.  You will have to decide
how much these premiums suit your pocket
or which plan suits you.
But according to me,
fundamentally these are the top three insurance
companies in our country and my
advice to everyone is that you should purchase
health insurance plan from the top health insurance company only.
Whatever queries you have related to these plans, whatever questions you have
, you can ask me
in my comment box.  I will meet you
in my next video.  Till then Jai Hind
Jai Bharat.